<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A nevv, cheape and delicate fire of cole-balles wherein seacole is by the mixture of other combustible bodies, both sweetened and multiplied. Also a speedie way for the winning of any breach: with some other new and seruiceable inuentions answerable to the time.</title>
            <author>Plat, Hugh, Sir, 1552-1611?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114744</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849967</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849967</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15148</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09732)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15148)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1328:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A nevv, cheape and delicate fire of cole-balles wherein seacole is by the mixture of other combustible bodies, both sweetened and multiplied. Also a speedie way for the winning of any breach: with some other new and seruiceable inuentions answerable to the time.</title>
                  <author>Plat, Hugh, Sir, 1552-1611?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Peter Short dwelling at the signe of the Starre on Bredstreet-hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the curteous and well disposed reader" signed: H. Plat Esquier.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Includes "A wooden vessell being as serviceable for the boiling of liquors as anie copper kettle, or other metalline vessell whatsoever".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Coal balls --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Implements, utensils, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15148:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15148:1"/>
            <p>A new, cheape and <hi>delicate Fire of Cole-balles, wherein</hi> Seacole is by the mixture of other <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtible bodies, both ſweetened and multiplied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo a ſpeedie way for the winning of any Breach: with ſome other new and ſeruiceable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions anſwerable to the time.</p>
            <q>Regium eſt cum feceris bene, audire male. <bibl>S. Ha.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of coal balls burning on the hearth</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by PETER SHORT dwelling at the ſigne of the Starre on Bredſtreet-hill. 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:15148:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15148:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CVRTEOVS AND <hi>well diſpoſed Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing euerie way willing, though no waie able, out of my manie and manifold trauels to bring foorth ſome ſubſtantial and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious inuention for the auoiding of idleneſſe, and relieuing the preſent miſery, which the fortune of warres, together with the want of profitable labors hath brought vpon vs: I could not (on the ſodaine) bethinke my ſelfe of a better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie, then how to imploy the poore and maimed perſons of this land, who (hauing their hands only) might be ſufficiently able to worke vp theſe ſweet and profitable fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balles, for the benefit and pleaſure of the rich. And as I haue alreadie in my booke of Remedies againſt famine, freely and plainly deliuered, ſundrie new and cheape kinds
<pb facs="tcp:15148:3"/>both of meate and drinke to bee vſed in a dearth of victuall; ſo if now in the ſcarſitie of fewel I may alſo proue ſo happy, as to bring forth a cheape and ſauing fire to warme and cheriſh their cold and frozen limmes, with the recompence of their labours, I ſhall bee greatlie encouraged to deuote and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate the fruits of ſome of my intermiſſiue houres vpon theſe and ſuch like charitable and godly vſes. But without all queſtion if the rare and excellent ſpirits of this land, might haue their beſt inuentions by ſome act of Parliament priuiledged to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues for ſome reaſonable time, with ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable part of the gaines reſerued for the ſuccour of the poore (a matter well moued of late, but croſſed and ſwallowed vp, I know not how in the bare and naked word of <hi>Monopolies</hi>) I would not doubt, but though <hi>priuatum commodum</hi> be the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in euerie Artiſts intention (as it is in all manuall and mechanicall trades) yet that <hi>bonum publicum</hi> would alſo follow and flow abundantly in the execution and publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch ingenious deuiſes: out of which maine root manie large and plentifull bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb facs="tcp:15148:3"/>of gainfull imploiments, for idle and vagrant perſons, were by all probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence likely to ariſe and ſpring.</p>
            <p>In the meane time whileſt theſe long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued fauours doe yet remaine rather to bee wiſhed of all then hoped of anie, I haue thought good to kindle ſuch a fire, as I hope ere long will blaze in his full brightneſſe, both in the halles and cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of diuers Noble men and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of this land, who finding the great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene their former fires of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cole, and this newe and ſweete compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both themſelues, and by their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple alſo manie other perſons of inferiour qualitie, will bee readie as well for their owne good, as for the reliefe of their poore and diſtreſſed neighbours (which almoſt in euerie place of this land are readie euen with teares &amp; prayers to craue either chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or emploiment toward the maintenance of themſelues and their poore families) to giue all the beſt furtherance which they may, and that with all ſpeedie and diligent expedition.</p>
            <p>And ſo hauing ſatisfied your long and
<pb facs="tcp:15148:4"/>earneſt expectation in this my new concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fire, I hope you will affoord me the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence which I am to require at your hands, which is nothing els but <hi>veniam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munere poſco.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>H. Plat</hi> Eſquier.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:15148:4"/>
               <head>Seacole ſweetened and <hi>multiplied.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I diſcloſe the matter and maner in this new compoſition of Cole-balles, I thinke it verie neceſſarie, firſt (in the behalfe of thoſe poore and miſerable wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, for whoſe good I do prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally intend this Treatiſe) to intreat all ſuch Magiſtrates, vnto whom the care and prouiſion of fewell doth any way appertaine, that they ſo farre forth, as either their authoritie, skill, or trauell may giue anie furtherance hereunto; would be verie prouident and careful not to ſuffer anie ſeacoles to be ſold or landed at anie wharfe or key, vnleſſe the ſame by good experience ſhall be found to be of the beſt mines: or at the leaſt of ſuch kind and qualitie as will cake and knit together, and ſo make a hot and durable fire. For the better performance wherof, I hold it the plaineſt and moſt euident triall of all other, firſt to cauſe a conuenient fire to be made of ſome parcell of the coles of euerie ſhip, before the owner be ſuffered to vnlade, with a ſpeciall charge giuen, that if the whole bulke do not fall out to be of the ſelfe ſame and equall goodneſſe with the ſample, that the reſt ſhould either be returned or confiſcated, if any law or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of that place will beare it. For herein I my ſelfe haue beene a feelnig witneſſe, who at the firſt (not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing any skill in the choice of my coles) haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times bought ſuch, as I haue beene forced euen free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to giue to thoſe which could make any vſe of them,
<pb facs="tcp:15148:5"/>at which time no doubt many poore &amp; vnskilfull men did likewiſe to their great hinderance, and ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> almoſt to their vtter vndoing, make a moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable prouiſion for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; their poore wines and childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And if happily the Magiſtrat ſhal either grow negligent, or deale corruptly herein, then do I aduiſe euerie man to make the like triall for himſelf. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will no way be wanting in good will to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of ſo generall a commoditie as I haue now in hand, I will here ſet dowe ſome few examinations of mine owne, which may happily ſerue for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of all ſuch buyers, as haue no better experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then mine to direct them.</p>
               <p>Firſt I do hold it an infallible rule to know a good cole by, viz. if the ſame being held ouer a candle, or rather ouer a flaming fire, do melt, &amp; as it were drop or frie: for this is an argument of his fattie and ſulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious nature, which miniſtreth ſtore of foode for the fire; but if the ſame grow hard &amp; drie ouer the flame, it is a ſigne of a leane and hungrie cole, and ſuch as will not cake or knit in the burning: of which kind are the <hi>Sunderland</hi> coles, whereof the poores wharfe in London can giue a ſufficient teſtimonie; which haue lien one winter already without anie great decreaſe, ſauing that ſome parcell thereof hath rather beene tranſlated to another place, to make the bulke ſeeme leſſe, then ſold and diſtributed amongſt the poore, for whom that charitable prouiſion was firſt meant. Here xviii. pence or fiue grotes in the price of a chaldron was ill ſaued.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the brightneſſe and gliſtering of the cole both within &amp; without, is ſome argument of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (although I haue heard that ſome kind of bad ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cole
<pb facs="tcp:15148:5"/>newly digged out of the mine, and brought drie in ſommer time, will both ſhow and breake faire) but moſt commonly if it breake in the colour and luſtre of pitch, it proueth a good cole to the buier: but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion, if the ſame be of a darke, duskiſh, and dead earthly colour, it is vtterly vnprofitable for him that ſhal ſpend it.</p>
               <p>The laſt and moſt aſſured proofe of all the reſt (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the making of a fire with them, wherein no man of any ſenſe can eaſily be deceiued) is the lightneſſe of the coles in weight. This weight, as in manie other bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſo eſpecially in water, doth argue either his pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or his impuritie: for the lighter &amp; clearer water, is euer held the better &amp; more wholſom, as leaſt partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating with earth or minerals. Now if you haue but halfe a peck of the beſt &amp; lighteſt coles, finely powde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red alwayes remaining by you, with this you may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the goodneſſe of any other cole, and by how manie degrees it differeth from the ſame (the lighteſt coles being alwayes the beſt) the neerer your cole commeth in lightneſſe to the patterne (both being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually meaſured, &amp; brought to fine powder) you may aſſure your ſelfe that it is ſo much the better; and the more that the ſame meaſure of any other coles excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the other in weight, ſo much the more earthie &amp; worſe burning cole you ſhal find it. And thus much concerning the goodnes of the cole, wherein if the buyer happen to faile, then ſhall he labour in vaine, either to ſweeten, or multiply the ſame; the ſeacole it ſelfe being the <hi>baſis</hi> &amp; foundation of the whole work, which muſt giue both ſtrength and ſubſtance to the bals. And becauſe it is not impertinent to the ſubiect which wee haue in hand, to know the places of our
<pb facs="tcp:15148:6"/>beſt mines already diſcouered, &amp;c. I haue thought good heere to name the principall places or mines, from whence the beſt ſeacole is brought, <hi>viz. Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rham, Blaidon, Stillow, Redhew,</hi> and <hi>Bourne;</hi> the reſt being ten or eleuen more, are of a worſer kind, and the worſt of all are thoſe of <hi>Sunderland.</hi> I would the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of theſe pits or mines, would deale ſimply &amp; tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with vs: for by the report of many, that are acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their practiſes, there is ſuch a medley made of theſe mines, as no man can tell which is the predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant cole in the whole bulke.</p>
               <p>I haue here alſo a fit occaſion offered me to moue the right Honorable the Lord Maior of the Citie of London, and the right worſhipfull the Aldermen his brethren, that if this new fire of mine proue a ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and profitable inuention, according to that ſhewe and countenance which <hi>(prima facie)</hi> it ſeemeth to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that they would immediately vpon good proofe thereof, gather vp all the idle and vagrant perſons, &amp; all the maimed &amp; vnpenſioned ſouldiers, which (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all our new taxations &amp; contributions) do ſtill peſter the ſtreets and ſuburbs of this citie, and imploy them in their profitable labors in that vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable peſt houſe. And that which is here ſpoken for London, I hope wil alſo ſerue for all the houſes of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection within this realme, where there ſhal bee found ſufficient ſtore of matter to worke vpon.</p>
               <p>The laſt petition or requeſt which I do here make in the behalfe of the poore, is that at ſuch time as by the ſlender prouiſion of the Magiſtrate, and by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme hard, and froſtie winter enſuing, whereby great ſtore of feacole is ſpent (which doth oftentimes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen) that the Magiſtrats of all places would neuer ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="tcp:15148:6"/>or permit the cole it ſelfe to be ſold aboue the rate of three ſhillings gain vpon the chaldron to any cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger, which commonly falleth out (reſpecting the time of the forbearance of his money) to be at the leaſt 20. or 30. in the hundred, &amp; vpward, if you adde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto that fiue in the hundreth, which he gaineth by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer meaſure, when he buyeth a whole ſhips lading in the poole together.</p>
               <p>And if vſurie bee ſo dangerous a trade, as both the word of God and al the miniſters therof do daily pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and proclaime vnto vs, the ſame for the moſt part being drawne from men of good eſtate &amp; credit (for the vſurer will ſeldom truſt any other) what ſhall wee thinke of a double and treble vſurie, may of a doubling the principall it ſelfe (whereof there hath beene a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable &amp; wretched experience of late memorie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this honorable citie of London) &amp; that wrung out euen from the backs and bellies of the pooreſt ſort of people.</p>
               <p>I had thought alſo to haue ſpoken ſomwhat for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the cole ſacks, which (by the opinion of diuers men) do in drie and wet weather differ greatly from themſelues, and by that meanes cannot produce ſo certaine a meaſure to the buyer as the buſhel or fat doth, which is alwayes of one and the ſelfe ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: but I doubt not (if the allegation be ſound) but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wiſdom of the Magiſtrate will ſoon reforme this fault. But now to mine own part: wherein becauſe no Author of any new inuention (though hauing <hi>Lincius</hi> eyes, or enioying the piercing ſpirit of <hi>Mercurie</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) is able truly to foreſee all the future effects &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents that in time may happen to croſſe a matter of innouation or noueltie: I do here (expecting nothing
<pb facs="tcp:15148:7"/>els but a thankfull acceptation of my painefull and coſtly labours at your hand, if the ſecret proue rich and beneficiall to the poore, which is my hope and deſire, or els your gentle pardon if it fall out other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, which is the leaſt that I can deſerue) freely offer and publiſh the greateſt part of my knowledge in this kind, and ſo I proceede to the compoſition.</p>
               <p>In the winter ſeaſon after ſome few froſts, gather ſo much lome as will ſerue your houſe for one whole yeares ſpending (for then it will crumble and diſſolue more eaſily in water then at other times, although at all times with a little more labour in ſtirring the ſame it may be made ſeruiceable enough for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) half a peck, &amp; happily a leſſe proportion of this lome, diſſolued in a little tub of water, is a ſufficient quantitie for the knitting vp of a buſhel of ſeacole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to balles, and your water and lome incorporated and well laboured together muſt be like a very thin pap.</p>
               <p>Then take a buſhel of the beſt ſeacole, which bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrewed vpon a ſtonie or paued floore, you muſt breake or bruiſe with a hammer, mallet, or ſome other apt toole or inſtrument, or otherwiſe you may ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently powder them vnder your feete, which I haue found the readieſt and cheapeſt way of all other. This is entended of the greater ſort of coles; but if your coles be of the ſmaller kind, then are they ſufficiently prepared for this worke to your hand.</p>
               <p>Spread theſe coles abroad ſome handfull thicke, or thereabouts, equally vpon the floore, then ſprinkle ſome of your thinne pap all ouer the heape: then turne them with a ſhouell or a ſpade, and ſpread the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe as before, throwing more of your lomy liquor vpon them. Continue this courſe till you haue made
<pb facs="tcp:15148:7"/>the whole maſſe or lumpe of your coles ſoft enough to be wrought vp into balles, betweene your hands, according to the maner and making of ſnowbals: then place them one by one, ſo as they touch not ech other til they be thorough drie, which will be in a few dayes. Then may you pile or lay them vp in heaps in any conuenient place, where they may bee defended from raine, which if it ſhould fall in any great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie vpon them, they would be in danger to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued againe. And ſo you haue ſeacoles wrought vp into bals ſimply of themſelues, according to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Lukeland</hi> in Germanie: which forme of firing hath been in vſe with them for many yeares paſt, and doth as yet continue to this day, as I am credibly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
               <p>Heere happily the workeman may be taxed of a needles and vnprofitable labour, in that a conuenient fier may be made of ſeacoles only according to our vſuall manner without any further charge or labor, and it is an auncient and approoued <hi>Maxime</hi> aſwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſound Lawyers as alſo amongſt al good Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titians. <hi>Quod fruſtra fit per plura quod fieri poteſt per pauciora.</hi> But to giue ſome reaſonable ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I do firſt preſume that thoſe frugal &amp; thriftie <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> haue found ſome good vſe of their labours, or els they woulde long ſince haue diſcontinued the ſame. Secondly, I haue found in mine owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that ſuch fiers as conſiſt of bals be neither ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue in ſmel, nor yet in ſoile, as the ordinary ſeacole fires are. And if experience the vndoubted mother of truth will not ſerue to ſatiſfie doubtfull wittes in this point, but that they will alſo call for reaſon at my hands <hi>(quia turpe eſt philoſopho quidquam ſine ratione
<pb facs="tcp:15148:8"/>proferre)</hi> I will giue you my conceit freely either to be controlled or confirmed at your pleaſures. And therefore my opinion is, that the ſmoke which in our vſuall fiers dooth immediatly aſcend from the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coles vnprepared, muſt needs according to the foule and groſſe matter of the cole, be alſo foule and ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelfe. But when the ſmoake doth paſſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as it were ſearſed thorough the lome (which is the band that knitteth the coles together) it is then ſo refined and ſubtilated before his penetration, as that it either conſumeth and ſwalloweth vp, or els leaueth behinde it the groſſe reſidence of his owne nature, whereby that black kind of pepperingor ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cole duſt (if I be not greatly deceiued) is either wholy or for the moſt part auoided: being a matter of ſo great offenſe to al the pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t gardeins of Noblemen, Gentlemen, and Marchants of this moſt honorable Citie and the ſuburbes therof, beſides the diſcoloring and defacing of al the ſtately hangings and other rich furniture of their houſes, as alſo of their coſtlie and gorgeous apparell, as that I preſume though theſe my charitable and well intended labours ſhould on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly produce a remedie for this long and hitherto ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoideable miſchiefe, that yet they would be receiued with a ſufficient applauſe and liking of all men. Alſo the ſtirring vp of common ſeacole fiers after they are once caked and knit together dooth make a helliſhe ſmoke and ſmoder, diſperſing the ſmootie ſubſtance &amp; ſubtile <hi>atomies</hi> abroad into the aire, which in a fire of balls doth neuer happen, becauſe after they are once piled in ſuch artificiall manner as is hereafter expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, they continue a ſtrong and laſting fier without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny touch or remouing of them. Beſides the beautie
<pb facs="tcp:15148:8"/>of this fire dooth greately commend it ſelfe, whoſe forme and ſhape in my opinion doth far ſurpaſſe all other fiers whatſoeuer; whoſe bals being round and all of one equall bignes, when they are all truely pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced together, they do much reſemble the piles of ſhot as they ly in a moſt beautifull manner within the tower of London.</p>
               <p>But now to come to our newe and Engliſh fiers, ſuch as neither <hi>Germany</hi> nor any other forrain king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or country, did euer to my knowledge as yet ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vſe or inioy, being alſo more ſweete by many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees (as being wrought vp with mixtures of leſſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence) yea ſome very pleaſing and delicate, and fit for Ladies chamber, and alſo more profitable (their mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication being of leſſe price by a great deale then ſeacole it ſelfe) I wil here firſt begin with the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and laſting compoſition of all the reſt that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I could find, and ſecondy I will proceede to the ſweeteſt fire, and after that to ſome other cheape and worſe compoſitions, yet al being ſuch as in the dearth and ſcarſitie of other fewell may be commendably vſed and ſpent.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt and principall fire that I will commend vnto you, is a compoſition of ſeacole, and ſmall cole, or thorne cole eyther in equall proportion (which will make a reaſonable good fire) or els taking only a third part of ſmall cole to your ſeacole (which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the beſt and moſt durable fire of all the reſt) wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them into balls and knitting them with lome as is formerlie ſet down in your ſeacole bals that haue no other mixture: but if your thorne coles be of the biggeſt ſort you muſt firſt bruſe them a little vnder your feete, or els they will require ſome more paines
<pb facs="tcp:15148:9"/>in balling them. Theſe thorne-cole with carefull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion may be had in the ſummer for three halfepenſe the buſhel, farre vnder the price of ſeacole, beſides the addition of halfe a pecke of lome which giueth ſome increaſe to the bulke. Now leaſt ſmal coles by this meanes ſhould grow to a higher rate, al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may eaſily iudge how ſuddenlie by the planting or pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in of ſmal twigs of willow, ſallow, alder and ſuch other ſpeedy growing plants, in al ſuch places as may beſt bee ſpared and are fitteſt to increaſe them, what great ſtore and quantitie of this fuel may be had yeer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without any feare of ſcarſitie; ſo as vnleſſe we wil be wanting vnto our ſelues, we ſhal not need to want this part of our new firing. Alſo to eaſe the charge of your ſmal coles, you may take one parte of earth, and one part of ſmall-cole, and the reſt ſeacole; but this maketh not altogether ſo bright a fire as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond and ſweeteſt fire of al the reſt, but not ſo laſting as the firſt, is a mixture of the ſaw duſt of deale or firre boords amongſt your ſeacoles, either in a third, or a moitie, as you did in ſmall cole: vſing ſtil the firſt band of lome both in this and al the other compoſitions following. And the ſawduſt likewiſe of elme or oke may bee mixed with ſeacole and made vp into bals, and this maketh a verie good and ſweet fire.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Many haue thought my fire to conſiſt of ſeacole and Cowdunge, and one among the reſt hath ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured to publiſh the ſame, as beeing aſſured of my compoſition: but now you may ſee that raſh pens do ſoone run riot. Yet I do not vtterly diſlike this mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, becauſe it may alſo haue a place amongſt my
<pb facs="tcp:15148:9"/>cole-bals: but the matter thereof not being ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al enough to match with a ſeacole, cannot bring forth ſo laſting a fire as my firſt is, and the ſame ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing alſo ſome vſe already in the enriching of grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, can hardly be ſpared in ſome places to be conſumed into firebals. Yet (to ſpeake truly of it) it maketh a ſweete and pleaſing fire: and if you beſtow labor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough therin you may make colebals, with it and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cole, without any other bande.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Some would haue my multiplication to conſiſt of chopt ſtrawe and ſeacole, but that conceit I hold not to be worth a ſtraw: for what doth ſooner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume with fire then ſtubble and ſtraw, which are apt to catch, but vnapt to continue the flame which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Tanners barks broken and incorporated with ſeacole, are very like to proue a good fire, but this ſecret will haue no great extenſion for want of matter.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The remainder of an olde fire may be wrought vp into new bals, or els piled in the middeſt of a new fire to kindle the bals the ſooner, ſo that in this kind of firing there is no loſſe of coles at all.</p>
               <p n="7">7. How turfe in his own nature may be mixed with ſeacoles, I haue made no experience: but if the ſame be firſt charcoled, no doubt it will make both a ſweet and a laſting fire.</p>
               <p n="8">8. What the oozes will do either for the multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or binding of our colebals, I can not certeinly determine, only I haue thought good to mention them, and ſo leaue them to other mens labors.</p>
               <p>The laſt circumſtance which wee are to obſerue in this our new fire, is the manner of making the
<pb facs="tcp:15148:10"/>ſame; which though a man without direction might eaſily aime at, yet ſeeing I haue bin liberal in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I will not be niggardly in the forme thereof. And therefore for the better placing or piling of theſe bals, I do firſt lay bricks edge wiſe on my hearth one by one, each bricke diſtant a full inch from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to the breadth or compaſſe of the fire which I intend to make (theſe bricks doe both ſaue the harth from burning, as alſo are in ſteed of an iron grate to draw wind to the bals, to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> burn the better:) then do I place a rowe of faucon or ſaker ſhot for the neathermoſt rank (&amp; they which haue no iron bullets, may lay colebals in ſteed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) and then an other row of theſe bals vpon the neather moſt, and ſo I frame my fire to what hight and compas I thinke beſt; but I haue alwaies vſed to place each ranke in the forme of a ſemicircle; but within toward the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of my fire, I conuey a few ſhorte cleft peeces of a faggot ſtick, and a few charcoles with them, or char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coles alone, and there I begin to kindle my fire. It may bee this fire will beare an artificial core of ſtone, brick or iron, wherby the fewer bals may ſerue the turne: heere euery man wil pleaſe himſelfe with his owne fancie, and ſo I leaue him to his beſt conceite.</p>
               <p>Theſe bals may alſo be mingled among billets and charcole being wiſely placed, and though the aſhes bee this way loſt, yet I doubt not but they wil eaſily be requited in the ſauing of the fire.</p>
               <p>And thus I haue diſcouered the beſt part of my skil in this new fire of colebals; whoſe good enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement may happily one day drawe matters of greater worth from me, tending as wel to the inrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the ſtrengthning of this little Iland, whoſe Lady and virgin Queene the great and mighty Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah
<pb facs="tcp:15148:10"/>long maintaine and bleſſe, with al his heauenly fauors and glorious benedictions, to his honor, hir de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and our comfort.</p>
               <p>I hope though the principal ſcope of this diſcourſe doth only conſiſt in the bettering and altering of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cole, yet that I may alſo with good leaue diſcouer ſome profitable aduiſe in charcole and other fewel, and that no man wil be offended though I teach him how to raiſe an extraordinary gaine by planting of fire-wood, farre exceeding the vſurers reckoning both in commoditie and lawfulnes: yea I am fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, and that not by reaſon only, but by the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controulable M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtres of al truth, that euery pound laid out in this manner, wil by a natural kind of vſurie at the leaſt treble it ſelfe within the compas of ſeuen yeares; which in the ſecond and third returne (beſides the yeerely benefit after the firſt ſeuen yeers farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding 10. or 20. in the hundreth) is able to giue a good contentment to the moſt miſerable peni-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this land. The tree which I meane is a willow, whereof one plant in ſeuen yeares commonly brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth forth ſeuen plants, beſides other boughes and ſpray, that may be conuerted into fagots, charcole and ſmall-cole. This kind of husbandry proueth beſt in moſt vnprofitable and ſurrounded groundes, which may beſt indure a dead rent for ſeuen yeares, ſuch as were of late plentifully to be found in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflowed fennes of Lincolneſhire, wherof Captaine Louel by his skilful and induſtrious labours hath newlie won 33000. acres, beeing a moſt memorable and ingenious worke, and wel deſeruing hir Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties moſt gratious priuiledge conferred vppon him. I would that Erith marſhes had twentie yeeres ſince
<pb facs="tcp:15148:11"/>met with ſuch a workeman. It may be they haue bin hitherto reſerued for my Inning, whereat you ſhall ſee me aime vnhappily in ſome of my laſt lines. But me thinks I am now ſo farre entred into water-work, that I haue almoſt quenched the fire which I haue in hand. To returne therefore to our firſt diſcourſe, I ſay, that although there ſhal not bee found ſufficient ſtore of ſuch moiſt ground, whereon to plant whole woods of willowes, yet I doubt not but if the bare and naked banks about all the ditches in Rumney marſh, and all the riuers, brookes, ditches, pooles, and marſh grounds of England beſides, were wel repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with Willowes, Sallowes, &amp;c. but that in a fewe yeares ſpace we might in ſome good meaſure ſupply the woodfals that haue beene committed in fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, and ſo bring downe the price both of billet, charcole and ſmall cole.</p>
               <p>And thus much as a cole-maker: I will now alter my trade, and play the Cooper another while.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:15148:11"/>
               <head>A wooden veſſell being as <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable for the boiling of liquors as</hi> anie copper kettle, or other <hi>metalline veſſell whatſoeuer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue thought good at this time alſo to touch my wooden veſſell, long ſince mentioned in my <hi>Iewell-houſe;</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would ſort it with a fire of mine owne fancie (as though it could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the moſt vſuall and ſtrongeſt fires that other me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talline veſſels and kettels are able to beare) but partly for that (being a matter of new inuention) it doth wel become this place; but principally, for that within a terme or two, I purpoſe (God willing) to make a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſhew thereof to all commers, vnto whom the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret it ſelſe ſhall alſo be reuealed and made good: and therefore I do here labour to prepare their minds to a kind and probable conceit therof, leaſt when it ſhall be offered to a publike view, it may happily bee taken for the ſecond part of M. <hi>Venners</hi> Tragedie, late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acted at the Swanne on the banke ſide, with better profite to himſelfe then pleaſure to the beholders.</p>
               <p>And becauſe ſeuetal men haue conceiued ſeueral and ſtrange opinions herein, ſome expecting a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous preparation of the wood, ſome doubting the durabilitie thereof (of the which ſort for the moſt part I find the Copperſmiths, who are vnwilling to beleeue anie thing that maketh againſt their trade and liuing) others charging the Author, as not hauing hitherto diſcloſed anie matter of worth, anie way anſwerable
<pb facs="tcp:15148:12"/>to the glorious titles of his bookes, and ſo (arguing, <hi>re ad perſonam</hi>) do vtterly condemne this ſecret with the reſt: &amp; ſome imagining the ſame both to be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and durable, but yet ſo curious, as that ſimple wits are neuer able to repaire it, being once out of frame: al theſe, I ſay, are either in ſome meaſure to be ſatisfied, or els they may well conclude, that I haue hitherto told but a tale of a tub. All which obiections (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I haue elswhere ſufficiently anſwered) yet once againe I will curſorily runne them ouer; that I may cleere both my ſelfe and the inuention of all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt, malicious, and ignorant calumniations, And here (not only to relie vpon the graue cenſure of the right honorable the Lord high Treaſurer of England, my good Lord and maſter, who vouchſafed me his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable preſence at my houſe, when both my fire, tub, portable pumpe, and boulting hutch were made readie for his comming; whoſe good approbation only is able to counterpoiſe and ouerwey the ſhallow and light conceits of all my aduerſaries) to the firſt I anſwer, that my defence is meerely naturall, and not drawne from that chargeable and incombuſtible oyle of <hi>Talcum,</hi> fitter to bee thinly laid vpon the face of a Ladie, then groſly ſpent or dawbed vpon the ſides of a wooden veſſel, nor yet from the haire of a Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whoſe bodies are rare and hard to come by. Yea it is ſuch, as vpon the diſcouerie wil proue ſo eaſie and familiar, as that I feare the beholders will rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne their owne weakneſſe, then wonder at my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, and yet the ſame both royally and really per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
               <p>And as for the durabilitie thereof, I will make this warrant to all that ſhall haue cauſe to vſe it, that how
<pb facs="tcp:15148:12"/>long ſoeuer anie wooden veſſel wil laſt that is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually employed about cold water, the ſame ſhal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure as long, though in the like maner exerciſed in the heating or boiling of liquor. And ſo I dare boldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, as ſometimes heretofore I haue done, that if my wooden Salamander were not more endangered by the element of water, then it is by the element of fire, we ſhould not need new veſſels but for new ages.</p>
               <p>The third ſort of cauillers, becauſe they ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be only carping Sophiſters, &amp; no ſound logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, as arguing from the matter to the perſon, &amp; ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logizing vpon particulars, <hi>in hoc &amp; in illo errauit, Ergo in omnibus.</hi> I hold them ſcarcely worth the anſwering: and yet becauſe I wil haue no aduantage taken of my ſilence, though I might anſwer them, as others haue done before me to the like: <hi>Carpere vel noli noſtra, vel ede tua.</hi> Yet leaſt that great and coſtly Mill in Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger lane, where the horſes trampling vpon a moueable floore, did euen with feare and trembling ſpend and waſt their ſpirits: or that monſtrous timber ſtote that ſhould haue blown vp &amp; diſperſed the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſquadrons, but now lieth rotting in his own ruins not worth either the time or timber that was conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in it, together with ſome other martiall engines, whereof there hath bin a great and long expectation without anie good &amp; ſeruiceable vſe made of them, (ſo as hitherto they do nothing els but <hi>ludere hiantem coruum</hi>) I ſay, leaſt theſe &amp; a few other of the like kind and qualitie, ſhould in the gulf of diſgrace drowne all the credit &amp; future hope of other Artiſts; that there are already, both by my ſelfe and other Engliſh-men, manie new, excellent, &amp; moſt profitable deuiſes both by writing, and otherwiſe made knowne to the world:
<pb facs="tcp:15148:13"/>whereof ſome are not ſufficiently as yet vnderſtood, moſt of them not regarded, and in a manner all of them, either not at all, or verie ſlenderly rewarded: I meane not with penſion, for that were chargeable, nor with fauours, becauſe they are not vſual, but with thanks, which is the baſeſt recompence that Arte may looke for. But you require ſome inſtances of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars at my hands, what ſay you then to ſuch a cariage for a cannon, whereby the peece with the helpe of two men only may be turned, maſtered, and charged at pleaſure in as good ſort as ten men are able to doe at ſea with their vſual cariages? What thinke you of a portable boate, which one man may carie with eaſe, and yet wil hold eight perſons? And of a light, ſtrong &amp; ſodaine bridge to be made by vniting theſe boates, and thereby ſodainly to conuey euen a whole armie ouer a large riuer? What if an inuention bee ſhewed how a ſeruiceable veſſel may chace with ten or twelue great peeces of ordinance as readily, and as aptly, as now any ſhip doth with two or with foure peeces on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? What if ſuch new kind of ſailes be deuiſed, as ſhal verie neere double the way which anie ſhip now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth? Nay, what if ſuch a Pinneſſe were warranted to be made, as ſhould vpon her owne motion, without the helpe of any mariner to direct her, make a ſpeedy way againſt all wind and weather vpon the ſeas for one halfe mile at the leaſt, and being laden with all kind of ſhot and fire-worke, vpon the firſt touch of any other veſſel, ſhal preſently giue fire to a traine, and ſo ſpend her ſelfe, and endanger ſuch ſhips as are then next vnto her? And what would you ſay to a peece of ordinance which one man may ſufficiently manage, and yet twentie of them ſhal make fiue hundred Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettiers
<pb facs="tcp:15148:13"/>to abandon the field? But to conclude theſe warlike inuentions with a ſhot of the higheſt executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both for land &amp; ſea. What if a bullet bee deliuered that ſhal breake into a thouſand parts, each part cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both his fire, powder &amp; ſhot with it, ſo as no gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon vnder the wals of any warlike towne or citie, no band of ſouldiers lying in the ſafeſt trenches they can deuiſe to make, can poſſibly be free from the furie of this bullet: which becauſe it may be ſhot compaſſe at anie reaſonable diſtance, muſt needes force them to forſake their ground.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Some of theſe new inuentions the Author hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewed to diuers of his honorable and priuate friends, and the reſt vpon reaſonable reward ſhall bee made good for any publike ſeruice; I could wiſh that ſome profitable vſe of this Gentlemans wit were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently made whileſt God doth ſpare him on earth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs; for I feare, when death hath depriued vs of this worthie Inginer, he wil ſcarcely leaue any true ſucceſſour of his skil behind him.</p>
                  <p>In this military kind of knowledge, if I ſhould not acknowledge mine own weaknes, it wold eaſily diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it ſelfe: &amp; yet I dare boldly ſay, that omitting many other ſecrets of good vſe, faithfully &amp; familiarly deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed for the benefit of the reader in my books alreadie publiſhed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my new &amp; late diſcouery in Peter-works being the true foundation and ground work of the laſt letters patents granted for the ſame; as it bringeth in yearly &amp; freely many 100. pounds to the Pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tees (my ſelf not hauing receiued one half yeeres profit for the inuention) ſo it, hath alſo eaſed the countrey of manie cariages, wherewith (by the ignorance of ſome Peter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in former times and yet to this day by the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:15148:14"/>of others) it hath beene and is now and then moſt grieuouſly oppreſſed, whereof it may be ere long I will find ſome ſufficient reliefe in a ſtrange maner.</p>
                  <p>But if the new (though natural) grounds of huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry were firſt wel vnderſtood, and after truly and painfully practiſed according to my printed direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; (leauing the conceit of digging and ſetting in a gentle ſlumber for a while) I would not doubt but that both for plentie of graſſe and corne this laſt age of ours wold far ſurpaſſe the dayes of al our anceſtors (excepting the golden age of Saturne only) &amp; yeeld ſufficient ſtore of corne both for our ſelues &amp; ſome of our neighbour countries. And this can two Engliſh Gentlemen of my knowledge yet aliue ſufficiently proue by their owne experience to be true, who haue aſſured me that for diuers of theſe latter yeares, they haue in a maner doubled the vſual yeeld of an acre, and that by plowing and ſowing only; al the inrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof not exceeding the charge of three ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings vpon an acre, toward which they haue alſo yeer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſaued the third parte of their ſeede corne, euery corne for the moſt part branching it ſelf into 10.15. &amp; 20. ſtalks and eares both large &amp; ful of graine: yea the colour and greatnes of the ſtalke and eare hath bin ſuch, as in harueſt time their corne (though one of their parts lay altogether in a common field) was ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſcerned from al other mens that enuironed the ſame. And where graſſe without exceſſiue charge would neuer exceed twelue inchesin height before, with the charge of foure ſhillings beſtowed vppon an acre, for foure years together there hath graſſe grown knee deepe and very plentiful.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>I had almoſte forgotten the winning of Earith
<pb facs="tcp:15148:14"/>marſhes, whereby alſo the breach made by a Cannon in the time of my ſiege though of fiue or ſix yardes in height and of twentie or thirtie in breadth, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently repaired and made ſufficiently defenſible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the enemie. And had the counſel of ſome men that I could name taken place in that infortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate voiage of Lisbone, whereby they had caried but the outſide of this ſecret with them, they might haue found lining enough to haue raiſed a fort euen vpon the ſands, and ſuddenly haue planted the cannon that ſhoulde haue commanded the towne it ſelfe. For ſo was the <hi>Golletto</hi> won by the Turke: a fort otherwiſe impregnable, whereby that honorable and glorious victorie of don Iohn <hi>de Auſtria</hi> obteined againſt the Turke by ſea, was mightilie eclipſed by a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ouerthrow at the ſame time giuen to the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans by land. Heere wee ſhal neither haue neede of nailes or timber, ſtones or morter, but linnen cloth &amp; needles to make our ſtrong defence either againſt the furie of the cannon or the ſourges of the ſea, the whole art wherof conſiſteth in bags or ſacks of linnen to bee filled vppon any preſent occaſion either with ſand or earth; and theſe to be ſuddenly layd or ſunke vpon any cauſe of ſeruice or irruption of waters. And though al the dutch marſh-men haue hitherto puſled themſelues about the inning and winning of the foreſaid breach, and haue giuen it ouer as impoſſible to be won at the Thames mouth (becauſe they find it in ſome parte to be nine or tenne foote in depth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath the low water-marke, before they come to any firme ground) yet I doubt not but by ſinking of ſacks of earth the workeman ſhal ſoone find or make
<pb facs="tcp:15148:15"/>a foundation ſufficient to beare a ſtrong marſh-wal, which may alſo conſiſt of ſacks of earth worke-manly placed, and after wel backed; which before the ſacks be throughlie rotten wil cloſely couch and knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and likewiſe be ſo fronted and filled vp with ooze, as that in a ſhort time you ſhal haue a firme and ſubſtantial marſh-wal againſt al wind and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whatſoeuer. There are alſo ſome other new and warlike vſes of linnen cloth, which may bee reſerued for ſome better occaſions then (thankes bee to God) theſe times doe as yet require out of which and ſome others which I haue partly ſeene, and partly heard of, I dare boldly conclude, that the moſt vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant armie of the beſt approued ſoldiers, (yea though conſiſting of louers themſelues, and that giuing bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile in the preſence of their Ladies and Miſtreſſes) may eaſily euen with a ſmal band of ingenious ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Artiſts be vtterly ouer thrown &amp; vanquiſhed. And therefore O happie and thrice happie are thoſe wits, (but moſt infinitely happie are thoſe kingdoms and countries which inioy them) who haue drawne and deriued their knowledge from the greate God of nature, from the firmament, from the foure ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, from the great Anatomie and from the little world, and the reſt of thoſe vnwritten books, whereof <hi>Paracelſus</hi> in his Labyrinth maketh a large and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>The laſt and leaſt obiection, wil be ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felled vpon the bare ſight and view of the veſſel, and I make no queſtion but that al the Coopers in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land wil be my ſureties in this behalfe, vnto whom I doe freely reſigne the gaines of my wooden tub for
<pb facs="tcp:15148:15"/>their general counterband, &amp; ſo I do leaue both them and the reſt of my contrimen in a wooden expectation for a while.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Nec omnes, nec omnia mihi placuere, cur ego omnibus.</q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>H. P.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15148:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15148:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
